

Eyad Alhudhaif

**Assistant Professor of Finance** 

# **Skills**

Python 7+ yrs.

LaTex, Stata, SQL 8+ yrs.

Web-scraping 3+ yrs.

Arabic Native

English Fluent

# **Education**

### Univ. of South Carolina

Moore School of Business

PhD, Finance (2021)

Dissertation: "Three Essays on Agency Costs in Corporate Finance".

Committee: Eric Powers (Chair), Allen Berger, Hugh Kim, Omrane Guedhami.

GPA: 3.63/4

#### **Indiana State University**

Scott College of Business MBA (2014) Finance Concentration. *GPA*: 3.94/4

### **King Saud University**

B.S. - Bus. Admin., 2010 Concentration Track: Financial Management. *GPA:* 4/5

# **Biography**

Eyad Alhudhaif is an Assistant Professor who brings a unique blend of research insights, teaching excellence, and technical prowess to the classroom and beyond. His research centers around corporate finance, where he dives deep into topics such as Capital and Debt Maturity Structures, Dividend Policies, and Corporate Governance. Most recent work involves textual analysis of financial disclosures and the various implications it has on classical corporate theory.

Beyond the traditional academic toolkit, Dr. Alhudhaif wields programming languages, such as Python and Stata, to various applications in his career. Whether it's automating financial analyses, building programs for clients, or implementing cutting-edge algorithms to his own work. He believes that the intersection of finance and technology holds an immense promise for reshaping the industry.

Dr. Alhudhaif isn't confined to lecture halls. In fact, he actively engages with industry practitioners and clients for consulting services, bringing real-world relevance to his teaching & research.

# **Affiliations**

### **Assistant Professor of Finance**

02/2022 - Present

College of Business Administration, Muzahmiyah Campus King Saud University

Teaching responsibilities are courses mainly taken by senior students. In addition, I was the academic supervisor for the Cooperative Training Program for 2 consecutive semesters. The position was an opportunity to receive important feedback from potential employers on what aspects of the education service we as faculties need to improve in order to graduate more competitiveness students in the job market.

### **Financial Consultant**

09/2023 - 06/2024

Malaah Financial Consulting Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

Providing consulting services to companies and individuals by increasing shareholder value and improving both capital efficiency & liquidity. Many of these services require capital budgeting, financial analysis, market research, and micro/macro economic data research.

#### **Research Assistant**

08/2015 - 12/2020

Moore School of Business University of South Carolina

Assisted the following faculties with research related tasks; Dongmei Li, Sergey Tsyplakov, Da Ke, John Hackney, and Matthew Souther. Tasks include webscraping, preliminary analysis, literature review, and essay reviews. Assisted Eric Powers in building a Monte Carlo simulation for his class assignment for several academic semesters.

#### **AACSB Assistant Coordinator**

05/2014 - 05/2015

Scott College of Business Indiana State University

Worked with the business college to document and ensure faculties' intellectual contributions meet AACSB's requirements for the five-year accreditation report.

### **Contact**

- Riyadh, Saudi Arabia
- +966 506102030
- ieyada@live.com
- Personal Website
- in ieyada
- **y** @iEya\_d
- 🜎 github.com/ieyada



# **Teaching Experience**

### Mathematics of Money & Investments (QUAN127)

College of Business Administration, Muzahmiyah Campus King Saud University

This course is designed to strengthen students' understanding of neoclassical theories in finance by introducing the mathematical principles and techniques behind essential concepts; such as compound interest, present value of money, hedging, arbitrage, and pricing financial contracts. By the end of the course, students will understand the mathematical underpinnings of various financial instruments and apply mathematical reasoning to solve practical financial problems. Mastering the material covered in this course can help prepare students for a career in either Financial Modeling or Financial Engineering.

### Case Studies in Finance & Investments (FINA423)

2022 - Present

2022 - 2024

College of Business Administration, Muzahmiyah Campus King Saud University

This advanced course is designed to extend and deepen students' practical understanding on a range of topics in the finance discipline. Students by the end of the academic semester will gain the ability to obtain, organize, and analyze financial data using computer software. Further, students' problem identification, engagement & participation within a team, and data analysis skills will all be improved by using both Python and Office Excel. By the end, students will have the ability to place policy recommendations based on their preliminary research findings.

### Portfolio Theory & Investment Analysis (FINA363)

2022 - Present

College of Business Administration, Muzahmiyah Campus King Saud University

The course provides an in-depth discussion of fundamental principles related to investment analysis and portfolio management. Topics include investment instruments, portfolio theory, equity valuation, fixed-income securities, and option valuation. Upon completion, students are expected to understand security market functions, recognize the risk-return tradeoff, and develop investment strategies. Further, mastering the material covered in this course will aid students in their preparation for the CFA exams level I.

### **Corporate Finance (FINA210)**

<u>2024</u> - Present

College of Business Administration, Muzahmiyah Campus King Saud University

Being one of the core subjects in any modern finance college program, this course aims to introduce a foundational understanding of corporate finance principles to undergraduate students. As such, the course equip students with essential tools that aid in business decision-making. Through a blend of theory and applications, students will explore key corporate decisions, such as capital budgeting & investments, financing, optimal capital structure, and dividend policy.

# Investment Analysis & Portfolio Management (FINA469)

Summer 2017 & 2019

Moore School of Business University of South Carolina

The course provides an in-depth discussion of fundamental principles related to investment analysis and portfolio management. Topics include investment instruments, portfolio theory, equity valuation, fixed-income securities, and option valuation. Upon the completion of the course, students are expected to understand security market functions, recognize the risk-return trade-off in investments, and able to develop investment strategies. Further, understanding the knowledge covered in the course help students prepare for the CFA exams.

*Number of students:* 19, Evaluation score: 4.55/5.

#### **Business Statistics I (BUS205)**

Fall - 2014

Scott College of Business Indiana State University

An introductory business statistics course. Topics include graphical concepts, measures of central tendency and dispersion, basic probability concepts, random variables, central limit theorem, and hypothesis testing and confidence intervals. Learning is assisted by statistical software applications. The emphasis is on problem solving for decision making.

*Number of students:* 30, *Evaluation score:* 3.77/5.

# **Working Papers**

- Alhudhaif, Eyad. (2021). "The Asymmetry Between Growth Opportunities and Debt Maturity Structure". Working Paper.
  - https://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3906487.
  - Using the recent public health pandemic (COVID-19) as a laboratory experiment, I find evidence of an asymmetrical relation between a firm's debt maturity structure choice and its growth opportunities. Firms with high pre-pandemic exposure to growth-inducing factors obtained from 10-K filings have increased debt maturity and are more likely to exercise a call on their callable bonds, while firms with high pre-pandemic exposure to growth-reducing factors are null in taking any actions to adjust their debt maturity structure. Further, the increase in debt maturity following exogenous changes in growth opportunities suggests a unique type of change in firms' growth options following the recent pandemic, supporting the arguments proposed by Diamond and He (2014) and Childs, Mauer, and Ott (2005).
- Alhudhaif, Eyad. Berger, Allen. Kim, Hugh. (2021). "Firm Risk Exposure Concentration and Debt Structure Choice". Working Paper. Firms with more risk shifting problems due to the high-risk exposure concentration are likely to include more short-term debt in their capital structures and less covenants in their outstanding bonds. Using a firm's risk exposure concentration derived from the written text in 10-K filings, we find this effect is more pronounced among companies with strong managerial incentive alignment with shareholders. The findings suggest maintaining future investment flexibility is important for firms with high-risk exposure concentration, even at the expense of a higher liquidity risk associated with the use of short-term debt.
- Alhudhaif, Eyad. (2016). "Corporate Payouts Under Economic Policy Uncertainty". Working Paper.
  - Using a sample of all public firms in the U.S. between 1985 and 2015, I examine the relation between firm's payout policy behavior under changes economic policy uncertainties, both total and individual components of payouts; dividends and

open market share repurchases. Using the EPU index and its components developed by Baker et al. (2016), I find payout programs tend to respond differently depending on the source of economic uncertainty. A persistent negative relationship exists between the level of uncertainty in government spending (GSU) and firms' average level of dividends, share repurchase, and total payout.

# **Projects**

• Developed an application (**Malaah\_app**) for *Malaah Financial Consulting*. The simple program serves as a helpful tool for the employees in the office to determine the appropriate financing products their clients can buy.

# **Involvements & Awards**

- Mentored students in the "Distinguished and Talented Students Program", King Saud University (2023)
- APICS Great Lakes District Student Case Competition; ranked 4<sup>th</sup>, Indiana State University (2014)
- Beta Gamma Sigma Award, Indiana State University (2014)
- Secretary of the MBA Association, *Indiana State University*, (2013-2015)
- Member of the Association for Operations Management, *University of Indianapolis Student Chapter* (2013)
- Member in the Investment Club, *Indiana State University*, (2013-2014)
- Outstanding Student Award, University of Washington (2011)

## References

• Eric A. Powers, Chairperson, Finance Department

The Moore School of Business

University of South Carolina

Columbia SC, 29208

Phone: +1 (803) 777-4928

Email: epowers@moore.sc.edu

• Allen N. Berger, Carolina Distinguished Professor

The Moore School of Business

University of South Carolina

Columbia SC, 29208

Phone: +1 (803) 576-8440

Email: aberger@moore.sc.edu

• **Kuntal Bhattacharyya**, Executive Director of Graduate Programs

Scott College of Business

Indiana State University

Terre Haute IN, 47809

Phone: +1 (812) 237-3588

Email: Kuntal.Bhattacharyya@indstate.edu

12th October 2024				
		1 4 11	11	: 6